<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prosopopoeia. Or, A conference held at Angelo Castle, between the Pope, the Emperor, and the King of Spaine</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115438</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850657</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850657</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10165)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 971:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prosopopoeia. Or, A conference held at Angelo Castle, between the Pope, the Emperor, and the King of Spaine</title>
                  <author>Paul V, Pope, 1552-1621.</author>
                  <author>Matthias, Holy Roman Emperor, 1557-1619.</author>
                  <author>Philip, II, King of Spain, 1578-1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse satire.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Satire, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:15878:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROSOPOPOEIA.</hi> Or, A CONFERENCE held at <hi>Angelo</hi> Caſtle, between the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>VVElcome deare Sonnes, vnto our court of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>bleſſing Apoſtolique and holy doome,</l>
               <l>ſheild all the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> from miſchanee,</l>
               <l>And both their fortunes and your crownes advance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour.</speaker>
               <l>Thy feet moſt holy Father doe I kiſſe.</l>
               <l>Of Church benediction if I miſſe,</l>
               <l>th'Imperiall Crowne from <hi>Auſtria</hi> will be gone,</l>
               <l>which heav'n forbid: for then w'are all vndone.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bohemias</hi> rebells with <hi>Hungaria</hi> joyne</l>
               <l>the Hereticks from <hi>Danow</hi> to the <hi>Rhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>their heades, their armes, their forces they combine,</l>
               <l>'gainſt <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Auſtria:</hi> Oh the <hi>Palatine!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>that curſed <hi>Calviniſt</hi> with his partakers,</l>
               <l>thoſe damned Schiſmaticks the Church forſakers,</l>
               <l>vpon our ruynes ſeeke to build their fortune,</l>
               <l>which makes me thus your Holines importune.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>The keyes of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the ſword of <hi>Paul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ſhall ſhut, and open, cutt in ſunder all:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15878:2"/>
               <l>the gates of heaven, nations lawes, and rights,</l>
               <l>and turne cleere daies, into the darkeſt nights;</l>
               <l>ere one of <hi>Caluines,</hi> or of <hi>Luthers</hi> ſect,</l>
               <l>with <hi>Romaine</hi> Bayes, or Aegles ſhall be deckt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour.</speaker>
               <l>The threates and curſes of the <hi>Catholiques,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>are now deſpis'd by theſe vile <hi>Heretiques:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>help by your counſell therefore <hi>Holy Sir,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>and ſhew us meanes to quiet all this ſtir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>Thou maiſt by reaſons, and Embaſſages,</l>
               <l>by queſtions, anſwers, and like paſſages,</l>
               <l>winne time a while, but theſe are out of date:</l>
               <l>Now ſwordes, not wordes, doe Kingdomes arbitrate.</l>
               <l>To neighbour friends, and ſubjects quickly ſend,</l>
               <l>that from ſurpriſe, thou maiſt thy ſelfe defend.</l>
               <l>My <hi>Nuntios</hi> and my <hi>Legats</hi> Ile diſpatch,</l>
               <l>more forces'mongſt the <hi>Catholiques</hi> to hatch,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ments, Colen, Trier,</hi> Catholique <hi>Baviere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>haſt thou in <hi>Germany,</hi> with other there;</l>
               <l>Thy vncle <hi>Albert,</hi> and the <hi>Poliſh</hi> King,</l>
               <l>vnto thee quickly may their forces bring.</l>
               <l>And though my ſelfe with <hi>Florence</hi> may not ſend</l>
               <l>our armes ſo ſoone; yet money will we lend.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cantons</hi> of the <hi>Switzers</hi> ſhall be wag'd,</l>
               <l>which to our See doe holde themſelves engag'd;</l>
               <l>ſo is the <hi>Saxon</hi> Duke with his eſtate,</l>
               <l>to thee in <hi>Dreſden</hi> and th'<hi>Electorate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>whoſe elder coſins hopes will make him feare,</l>
               <l>and to thy fortunes, and thy houſe adhere:</l>
               <l>Ile alſo ſend to <hi>Savoy,</hi> and to <hi>Venice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>to <hi>France</hi> our eldeſt ſonne, and to S. <hi>Dennice,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15878:2"/>
               <l>Ile fetch the ſaints from heav'n, <hi>The fiends from hell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Flectere ſi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queo ſisperos, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eronta mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uebe.</note>
               </l>
               <l>but Ile thoſe drunken <hi>Germane</hi> traytors quell:</l>
               <l>Beſides thy Spaniſh coſin preſent here,</l>
               <l>whome <hi>Europe</hi> and the new found world doe feare,</l>
               <l>the Churches <hi>Atlas,</hi> and the Empires prop,</l>
               <l>by ſtrength, by wit, by friends, or golde will ſtop</l>
               <l>theſe proud attempts and darings of the Dutch,</l>
               <l>and break their forces, coſt it nere ſo much.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. of Spaine.</speaker>
               <l>If <hi>Caeſar</hi> and your <hi>Holines</hi> have donne,</l>
               <l>obſerue the anſwer of your Spaniſh ſonne.</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Germane</hi> Prelates, nor <hi>Bavarie</hi> can,</l>
               <l>nor King of <hi>Pole,</hi> your ſelfe, nor any man,</l>
               <l>nor <hi>Tuskans</hi> Duke, nor <hi>Albert</hi> my poore brother,</l>
               <l>nor <hi>Cantons</hi> Catholique, nor any other,</l>
               <l>bring timely ſuccours, gainſt the conjuration</l>
               <l>thoſe <hi>Almaigne Graves</hi> have made in every Nation.</l>
               <l>Expect not help from <hi>Savoy,</hi> nor <hi>Venetia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>who feare and deadly hate the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I looke for nothing from my ſonne of <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>for if he ſaw vs downe hee'd ſing and dance.</l>
               <l>And why ſhould you from <hi>Saxon</hi> hope for more,</l>
               <l>then <hi>Charles</hi> my grandſire reap'd from his before;</l>
               <l>who gave him all, and more then you doe mention:</l>
               <l>yet ſhortly after in the great contention,</l>
               <l>twixt him and <hi>Germane</hi> rebels, he forſooke</l>
               <l>his <hi>Benefactor,</hi> and againſt him tooke.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Caeſar</hi> if at home thou look'ſt for ayde,</l>
               <l>thy <hi>Kingdomes</hi> both are loſt, thy ſtrength decayde.</l>
               <l>Thine <hi>Auſtrian</hi> ſubjects alſo are infected</l>
               <l>with <hi>Luthers</hi> hereſie, and have rejected</l>
               <l>the Papall dignitie, and may doe thine,</l>
               <l>and with their fellow <hi>Lutherans</hi> combine,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15878:3"/>
               <l>and if for ſuccour thou doe ſend to <hi>Thracia;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>the faithleſſe <hi>Turkes,</hi> thou know'ſt doe not loue <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spayne</hi> then muſt help, or what will Caeſar doe?</l>
               <l>and how ſhall <hi>Spaine</hi> helpe <hi>Rome</hi> and Caeſar too?</l>
               <l>Shall <hi>Indian</hi> armies, be recall'd from thence,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Italian</hi> forces march away from hence,</l>
               <l>leave <hi>Millaine, Naples,</hi> and our ſiluer fountaines</l>
               <l>vngarded, naked, to march ore the mountaines?</l>
               <l>Through <hi>Griſons</hi> countrey lead the ſtrength of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>or venture our <hi>Armada</hi> once againe,</l>
               <l>to narrow Seas, and ſo at once looſe more</l>
               <l>then we haue got, in ſixſcore yeares before?</l>
               <l>So thou at <hi>Auſpourgh,</hi> I in <hi>Arragon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>may ſhave our crownes, turne Monks, and liue alone.</l>
               <l>You count your friends, but count not all your foes,</l>
               <l>whoſe ſtrength, whoſe number, you cannot oppoſe:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Northern</hi> tract of <hi>Europe</hi> from <hi>Britania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>tending to <hi>Eaſt,</hi> as farre as <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(ſave <hi>Poleland</hi> and ſome trifles) is their owne,</l>
               <l>aye me, in foureſcore yeres how they are growne.</l>
               <l>Their Kingdomes, <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> bee,</l>
               <l>with <hi>Denmarke, Norway, Sweden,</hi> ſix you ſee:</l>
               <l>beſides thoſe two which they have wonne from thee,</l>
               <l>being eight in all, and our Kings are but three.</l>
               <l>The number of their <hi>Princes, Dukes,</hi> and <hi>Countes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>with their free <hi>Lords,</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> ours farre ſurmounts:</l>
               <l>beſides their many <hi>Palſgraves,</hi> and <hi>Burghgraves,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>with all their <hi>Lantgraves, Reingraves,</hi> and <hi>Markgraves.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as their numbers, ſo their ſpirits are,</l>
               <l>made great with hopes,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1618.</note> by the <hi>Prodigious ſtarre:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>which <hi>Blazed</hi> over <hi>Almaigne</hi> laſt <hi>December,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>portending change of ſtates; and I remember</l>
               <l>their expoſitions, and their calculations</l>
               <l>of times, of Scriptures, and of ſituations.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15878:3"/>
               <l>of <hi>Rome,</hi> of <hi>Babel,</hi> and of hilles and dales,</l>
               <l>of beaſts and dragons, and ſuch fearefull tales:</l>
               <l>wherewith they cheare themſelves, and their new King,</l>
               <l>as if they <hi>Victors</hi> were, and bells doe ring.</l>
               <l>Alas for <hi>Rome,</hi> alas for <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Alas for <hi>Philip,</hi> muſt he needes withſtand</l>
               <l>his owne, the <hi>Empires,</hi> and the Churches foes,</l>
               <l>and ſo himſelfe, the Church and <hi>Empire</hi> loſe?</l>
               <l>Haue all my Anceſtors to fiue deſcents,</l>
               <l>by Conqueſt, wedlock, and like ligaments,</l>
               <l>ty'de <hi>Earledomes, Dukedomes,</hi> Crownes and <hi>Empire</hi> faſt,</l>
               <l>hoping for <hi>Weſterne Monarchie</hi> at laſt:</l>
               <l>and is the period of our greatnes paſt,</l>
               <l>and our declyning now begin to haſt?</l>
               <l>Ah <hi>Naſſau, Naſſau,</hi> hatefull Sonne and Father;</l>
               <l>Curſt be your name and houſe, you, you did gather</l>
               <l>the hatefull rebells, into warlike bands:</l>
               <l>who now doe <hi>State</hi> it in our <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There, there you wrote <hi>nil Vltra</hi> once againe,</l>
               <l>and ſet vp <hi>Eſterne</hi> pillars, barres to <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour.</speaker>
               <l>Thus are our dangers, thus our feares related:</l>
               <l>thus be our mindes perplext, our hearts amated.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Rome</hi> haue any ſecret wiſedome hid</l>
               <l>layd vp for wicked times, or euer did</l>
               <l>make wicked heretiques feele Churches power,</l>
               <l>then Father now's the time and this the houre.</l>
               <l>Remember how two <hi>Fredericks</hi> heretofore</l>
               <l>'frighted thy predeceſſors, this may more</l>
               <l>hazard thy fortunes, vtterly ſuppreſſe</l>
               <l>the Romane Church, thy ſelfe, and vs (vnleſſe</l>
               <l>by ſome prime Stratageme) fetcht from the deepe</l>
               <l>thou doſt thy ſelfe and friends from danger keepe.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:15878:4"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And are our friends ſo few and ſo vntruſtie?</l>
                  <l>and be our foes ſo many and ſo luſtie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>One <hi>Innocent</hi> of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome</hi> in former ages,</l>
                  <l>hath us'd three Kings for lackeys and for pages:</l>
                  <l>And dare they now againſt our liking make</l>
                  <l>both Kings and Kaeſars? then you furies wake:</l>
                  <l>Help me to ſtore of piſtols, poyſons, knives,</l>
                  <l>to fyre and powder, manacles and gives.</l>
                  <l>Bid <hi>Ravilltack</hi> and <hi>Clement</hi> hye them hither,</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Gerad, Faux,</hi> and <hi>Garnet</hi> come togither;</l>
                  <l>Come ye <hi>Ignatians</hi> bring <hi>Aſſaſinates,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>left handed <hi>Ehuds,</hi> that doe rule the fates,</l>
                  <l>and cut the threds of Princes lives a ſunder:</l>
                  <l>theſe Romane <hi>Scauola's</hi> ſhall make men wonder</l>
                  <l>to ſee the upſtart King with his partakers,</l>
                  <l>in euery nation ſlaughtred by maſſacres.</l>
                  <l>Ile raiſe up <hi>Swarez,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. Famous <hi>Ieſuites.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Parſons, Bellar mine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loyallas</hi>-ſelfe their father: and refine</l>
                  <l>all humane witt to one pure quinteſſence,</l>
                  <l>againſt whoſe vertue ſhalbe no defence.</l>
                  <l>Therefore fayre Sonnes at nothing be diſmay'd,</l>
                  <l>remember what your Father now hath ſayd:</l>
                  <l>You to <hi>Vienna,</hi> you to <hi>Civil</hi> goe,</l>
                  <l>helpe as you may to giue the fatall blowe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. of Spaine.</speaker>
               <l>Come <hi>LLerma:</hi> looke not ſadly on thy friend</l>
               <l>But let's with Spaniſh patience waite the end.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:15878:4"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
